hello
and can you hear me
okay excellent sorry for the delay so
there was some
connection problem
okay
so if you so let me double check okay so
welcome all for coming
okay let me double check so if you can
hear me clearly could you please give me
some response could you please type a
one
okay thanks very much okay
so
so so for today so we will talk about
something that is related to the
content of
our first week's and lectures
thank you very much okay
so we have tried to receive your
questions during the weekend but perhaps
uh it's just the beginning of the
semester so you don't have a lot of
questions so i've prepared something for
you so it should be a very quick uh
tutorial today
and then if you have any questions there
please don't hesitate to ask me
okay so one key thing that we have
talked about
in the last class is something called
combinatorial arguments
so combinatorial arguments are something
that is
is a way of proving identities
so
i checked the wikipedia so mainly there
are two different categories of
combinatorial arguments
so the first one is called double
counting
so the double counting technique is we
try to count
the same quantity a value which talks
about the number of ways of doing things
we count it using two different methods
so in that case we will have two views
of the same quantity so that we can we
can get our desired result
and the other type of combinatorial
argument is the so-called bijective
proof
and for this one it is used to show that
two sets have the same number of items
so by
finding a one-to-one correspondence
between the items of the two sets we
will see that the two sets will have the
same number of items but this is not the
focus of today so we will talk about
double counting
and then we will look at a couple of
examples today
so this is
the easiest example probably
so in this example we want to show that
n choose k the value of n choose k
is always the same as the value of n
choose n minus k
now remember when we are doing
combinatorial arguments we do not have
any access to the
exact
formula for n choose k so we don't know
entries k is equal to something like
n factorial divided by k factorial and n
minus k factorial we don't know this
we just want to argue
the meaning from the physical meaning of
each of the terms
and then we want to establish the
equivalence of the both sides okay
so first of all n choose k is what n
choose k is the number of ways of
selecting k items from a total of n
items
so
by viewing of selection of k items to
keep
so it must be the same as
we are so when we try to keep k items so
it must mean that we are throwing away n
minus k items
so each time we keep a particular
set of k items we are actually throwing
the complements
n minus k items there
so the number of ways of selection of k
items must be done the same as the
number of ways of
discarding n minus k items so that's why
we have n choose k
is equal to n choose n minus k so this
is quite easy right
now let's take a look of this one
oh this is something that i just come up
now so so please help me to double check
whether this is correct
so here we are saying that n plus one
the permutation the number of
permutations of
uh p n plus one r
so this is like we have n plus one
objects to select
and then we want to select all of them
and then make an arrangement so the
number of ways of doing so
is always the same as
p n r plus r times
p n r minus 1.
so how do we interpret this result
so first of all we will see that on the
left hand side there is n plus one r and
on the right hand side there is n r
right
so m plus one r and n r they are
different by having one extra
objects here that we can select
so let's call it a special object
okay
so the number of ways of getting a
permutation with the special objects
that we can use
so we can classify this into two
different types
one is
we are going to use we are going to use
the special object
and then the other type is we are not
going to use the special object
okay so here n plus 1 means that we have
n original object plus one new object
that we can use okay
so
so the number of ways of not using the
special object must be p and r right
because we take that away we will not
consider it
so the number of ways of doing selection
of our objects from the old objects and
making an arrangement must be
p and r
okay for the other way
the other way is
so we must include the special objects
so by including the special object so we
will first decide
in which location will the special
objects be placed
because in the end
it is an r permutation there are
positions that these special objects can
be placed
so there are choices that we can make to
place a special object
and then for the remaining r minus 1
positions
we will need to fill in
r minus 1 objects from the old objects
so the number of ways of doing so is p n
r minus 1.
now notice that
again in the previous argument that we
have just made
we are not
looking at any formula for p and r
we are just arguing all the things based
on the definition of the term p and r
and then here we are using rule of
products
and the rule of thumb these basic rules
to help us to understand why this
equality must be correct
okay so let's take a look of another
example so so go home
so
if if you want to check your
understanding go home and cover all the
voices of this video and let's see if
you can
come up with the combinatorial ex proof
by yourself
now the next one is called the hockey
stick identity
so it is
saying that
ah
there was something wrong here i'm sorry
so
let me see so
sorry there is a mistake here
so it must be something like
this is
n minus 1
sorry
so every time here is n minus one okay
so let me go back again
so it says that
c n plus one
m m plus one object
choosing m object
must be the same as the summation of the
following terms
the first one is n choose n minus 1
and then the next one is n minus 1
choose n minus 1
and then the next one is n minus 2
choose n minus 1 and so on and so forth
we add up the things
until what until n minus 1 n minus 1.
so why is it so first of all before we
understand why this is correct so let's
understand why we call this a hockey
stick identity
so basically
this is the pascal triangle
that includes all the combinatorial
terms so one and one one and then one
two one and then one three three one one
four six one one and so and so forth
so the hockey stick identity says that
if you want to get the term
this term let's say a particular term
here let's say this is 10 times here the
term 10 here
so we can go
leftward
and one entry to the previous row
and then add up all these along the way
all these along the way so 1 plus 3 plus
6 will be equal to 10.
so let's look at this 10 again this 10
is equal to what this 10 is equal to 4
plus 3 plus 2 plus 1.
so how about this 5 this 5 is 0 to 1
plus 1 plus 1 plus 1 plus 1. how about
this 4 this 4 is equal to 3 plus 1.
so
so if we look at the terms that we are
considering it looks like the hockey
stick that we play in hockey
yeah the hockey stick here so that's why
we call it a hockey stick identity
so why is this correct
so again
here we can come up with a story okay
so there are n plus one items here that
we can select so let's label all the
items by one two three four five up to n
plus one
and then we want to select m of them in
total so how many ways are there
now the first term
is the case that we will never select
one so the the the item one is never
selected
i'm sorry so the item one must be
selected sorry this is the item one must
be selected
so the item
one must be selected the number of ways
that we can do so is
because one is already selected so we
will need to find out n minus one items
from the remaining n items to make a
total number of m items so we get this
term n and the n minus one
so this term here means
one is always selected
so for the remaining case
we will need to consider the remaining
case we will we can never select one
because whenever one is selected it is
already counted here
so this term is what this time is
one is not selected but two is selected
so in that case if one is not deleted
but two is selected then what does that
mean
so it means that we will need to find
out n minus one items from the remaining
n minus one items to make a collection
of m items
so this talks about the second term
talks about one not selected but two
selected
and then this is the third term the
third term consider the case that one
and two are both
not selected but we need to select three
so in that case we have this one
and and so on and so forth so lastly
this one
it means that
we will have one two three four five six
seven eight up to n minus one
they are let me see
they are
so so basically so this is this is the
case that a couple of items is not
selected and then and then and then what
what must be selected and so and so
forth so it means that the first
n minus m plus one items are not
selected
so that means that we have only a minus
and the end
i think you you understand what i mean
so so each of the term here corresponds
to
one more item cannot be selected so in
the end we have no choice so for the
remaining we have just a minus one items
left and so we need to select all of
them so this n minus 1 choose n minus 1.
okay so don't worry if you don't
understand what i'm talking about so far
so
most important thing here is
you can
go back home and then
do this by yourself
and then convince yourself that which
what each term
means okay so also what i'm given here
is just one example so you can have your
own story the the way of double counting
proof is
to make a story of what is the quantity
on the left-hand side and make a story
of what is the quantity on the
right-hand side and then we want to show
that these two uh
t these two different stories are doing
the same thing accounting the same
identities so that's why they are equal
so you can make your own story
okay so how about this
one okay so this one is n times n minus
1 choose r is always the same as
r plus 1 times
n choose r plus 1.
so here
so how do we interpret the things here
let's
so it may be a little bit complicated
but let's try to figure out what could
the potential meaning of the left-hand
side
so the left-hand side looks like what
looks like okay so there's n here and
then you multiply something that just
have n minus 1 to choose
so probably we may think of this as
let's say there are n people
in a in a in a class
and then we want to select one of them
as the representative
and after that
we want to select
and extra our people to be the to be the
committee member of of the class society
something like this
so all together that
so we need to select one people as the
representative let's say the chairman of
the class society
and then
are extra members for the class society
so there are n ways of selection of the
chairman out of n people
and then from the remaining n minus 1
people we need to pick out
so this is one way to form a class
society one chairman and then our other
members
now
we can also form a class society using a
different way
but then this is exactly doing the same
thing so what we are going to do here is
we first select all the members
including the chairman for the class
society and after that we pick the
chairman from these members
so how many ways of doing so
so that n choose our plus one ways to
select the chairman together with the
our members in the class society so
these are
forming the members of the class society
first
and then after that we have our plus one
people
and then we need to select the chairman
from from them so there are plus one
ways of doing so so this time we will
see that
the right hand side quantity is the
number of ways that we can form a class
society and the left-hand side is also
the number of ways of that we can form a
class society so they must be equal so
that's why they are equal again there is
no formula involved we are just arguing
things based on the rule of product here
rule of product here that's it
and now finally this is what i want to
introduce to you today so
so this is perhaps the most complicated
example
that we have
so this is actually a selected question
from
from our
exam
in 2019
so here we have a very complicated
summation thing
and then i didn't tell you
what this should be so you are not
proving this is
equal to what but instead
see if we can interpret
what is the summation sign here
so after doing the
the understanding of this we may be able
to find
an easy understanding of what this sum
could be
okay so this is the summation of let's
take a look okay so first of all this
time
bracket and i here simply means n choose
i so this is another shorthand notation
for c and i so n choose i
and then m minus i choose j
so what does that mean so first of all
let's take a look of this one so
forget about the summation let's
understand what this compound
this product means so it looks like the
n people that i want to pick i of them
and then from the remaining a minus i
people i want to pick j of them
okay so so here basically
we are
looking at something like we are trying
to
we are trying to
make the members the n members of people
into three different groups
so i of them
in the first group n choose i i of them
in the first group
right
and then
from the n minus i of them i choose j so
j of them in the second group
and finally n minus i minus j of them
in the third group
okay
now here for j is equal to 1 up to n
minus i minus 1 it means that
i'm selecting
the case that
j has to be at least one
and then j can be at most n minus i
minus one
so it means what it means that
the second group
and the third group cannot be
empty it must have some people inside
is that okay
now for here n minus n choose i here
when i ranges from 1 to n minus 2 it
simply means that the first group has at
least one people
is that okay n choose i one people
and up to n minus two people so that we
can have two people left for the second
group and the third group
so all together what does that mean
if you look at this summation sign
we sum up all the different cases
we are trying to
what we are trying to
to what to divide the group of n people
into three groups
okay
such that
each group is not empty
so how many ways of doing so
so any idea
so first of all if there are
no restrictions at all
the number of ways to divide n people
into three different groups
will be 3 to the power n
right
it is because
each particular person can be in group
one group two or group three
so
by rule of product so the first one has
three choice the second one has three
choice and so on and so forth so all
together they are three to the power and
different ways of
dividing the people into three groups
but then we want to avoid
people
so we want to avoid the case that
the first group is empty we want to
avoid the case that the second group is
empty and then we want to avoid the case
that the third group is empty so in that
case we need to do a little bit of
of what of corrections so 3 to the power
n is a little bit more than what we are
counting
so perhaps we have not done this before
but then we can
do something like the principle of
inclusion and exclusion that
i guess you have already studied in your
discrete math class
so by using the principle of inclusion
and exclusion
so the answer should not be just 3 to
the power n
it should be something like 3 to the
power n minus the cases where
one of the group is empty and then plus
the case where two of the groups is
are empty
and then minus the case where three of
the groups are all empty
so
so in that case this is my guess so you
can you can
double check whether this is correct at
home
so this is my solution okay so
let me write this
so this is my solution
my solution will be this one
is equal to
3 to the power n
minus the case that
exactly not exactly at least one of the
group is empty so let's say group 0 is
empty so if group 0 is empty so the the
the
sorry group 1 so let's say we call the
groups group 1 group 2 and group 3.
group 1 is empty so how many ways are
there there are two to the power m is
and then group 2 is empty they're 2 to
the power n ways root 3 is empty they're
2 to the power n base
but then we have
over deducted so we need to add back the
case where
group 1 is group 1 and group 2 is empty
so there are 1 to the power n
plus 1 to the power n
plus 1 to the power n something like
this so in the end this should be
something like so after simplification
this should be 3 to the power n ah maybe
let's see if i can use
a
how can i make it into
let me see format
one yeah i don't know how to how to
change it to the
superscript
there should be a symbol here let me see
let me see
and like this okay three to the power n
it should be something like this
minus 3
times
2 to the power n
and then finally
plus three
so
so this is what i would guess so
perhaps you can double check whether
this is correct or
so this is what i would guess
but to
yeah
but the way that we get this it is
because we have do the simplification to
do the understanding of what this term
could mean and because of this we can
have a good interpretation so that we
can use our existing knowledge to get
the answer
yeah i hope you like this so
combinatorial proof is very useful
because it avoids a lot of
difficult and computation so if you want
so
later we will have formulas for n choose
i n minus 1 minus i choose j something
like this but this is complicated if you
want to simplify them
not to mention that we have a lot of
summations here that we need to handle
but on the other hand if we have a way
to do this interpretation then
everything could be made easy
okay so i think that's all for what i
want to show today yeah because this is
the first week
but i want to mention one thing okay
so we are going to
assume that you will study the materials
of ocw recording and also the lecture
notes at your own pace by yourself so
roughly speaking
we will have three hour lecture normally
in a in a class so that's what we are
expecting you to to review
three hours of ocw recording every week
so on thursday
we will talk about a quick class summary
of the three hour lectures that you have
seen
and then on tuesday like this we will
answer any potential questions that you
want to ask us
or we will prepare something that is
interesting for you so tuesday class
normally will be very short
and that thursday class normally will be
very
quick okay but i hope if you find any
difficulties in the studying yeah please
let us know okay so meanwhile if you
have
any questions could you please
and
stand to the discussion board
here the chat room here
if not then yeah let's meet on thursday
and happy moon festival today
so because i don't see any questions so
let's end the class now okay thanks a
lot for coming okay and then and then
see you on thursday
okay